<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Courant newes out of Italy, Germany, Bohemia, Poland, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119519</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854726</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854726</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181298</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14941)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181298)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1133:7j)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Courant newes out of Italy, Germany, Bohemia, Poland, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By George Veseler. [sold by P. Keerius],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>The 15. of Iuly. [1621]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title. Vendor's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 5745.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 5745 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Bound and filmed with twenty-four other issues.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Europe --  History --  1517-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="newspaper__coranto">
            <pb facs="tcp:181298:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Courant Newes out of Italy, Germany, Bohemia, Poland, &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>From Venize the 25. of Iune, 1621.</head>
               <p>AT Mylane are come bills of Exchange fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Spaine / conteyning <hi>500000</hi> Crownes / and foure Compagnies of Souldiors are ſent to Deltlin.</p>
               <p>The Duke of Savoye hath given over his ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to his Prince / and onely retained to him ſelfe the Government of warre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>From Leon, the 20 of Iune.</head>
               <p>On Frydaye laſt is the declaration of the King in favour of the Proteſtants publiſhed / and they that will gaine the contents thereof / muſt declare whether they will hould with the King or them of Rochel / wee thinke that the Kinge will not beſiege it this yeare / but onely cauſe ſome For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes to bee made before it / and keepe ſome men of warre before it. To the ende there may no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing come into it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>From vvelis the 25. dito.</head>
               <p>The Lord Helmhart Georg is brought into Lints / where more other Lords alſo are arreſted many other Lords are likewiſe ſent for thither / for upon the <hi>9.</hi> of Iuly the whole Land over the Ens ſhall acknowledge his Highneſſe in Beye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren for their Prince / as an unobligated pane / af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which there is nothing to bee expected but a generall Reformation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>From vvaid hauſen, the 27 hereof.</head>
               <p>The whole Army of Manſvelt is inquartered here / and in the Villages heere abouts againſt the Borders of Bohemia. The Enimie ſheweth himſelfe dayly without our ſkonſes / which doth give blynde allarmes untill it is once in earneſt. Yeſterdaye is the Prince of Wymeren with <hi>1400</hi> Footemenne and ſix Cornetts Horſmen come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us. There is making a faire Schonce for us before the noſe of the Enimie / upon the borders of Bohemia / and every Souldior that laboureth thereon is payd above his meat and drinke <hi>3.</hi> batſes a day / when this Fortreſſe is finiſhed wee ſhall ſee whether it will be intended eſpecially / when all the Souldiors bee together. There are alſo <hi>7.</hi> Cornets of Horſemenne ordayned by the Captaine Paap at Amberg / the Enterprize is yet unknowne. The ſouldiors receive good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort / but as yet no monnye / by reaſon whereof the tyme might fall them to long.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>From Vienna the 23. of Iuny.</head>
               <p>The Emperours Majeſtie (accompanied with many Nobles / is gone from hence the <hi>18.</hi> hereof yearly in the morning to Zell / before the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours departure the King of De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>markes Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours tooke there leave / and ſo departed home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes / it ſeemes they have not effected much for the King of Bohemia.</p>
               <p>The Generall Bucquoy lies yet before Nieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heuſel / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d proceedeth dayly in making of Schon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes / the Governour Diepenbach hath taken from them the milles / though the beſiedged have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>8000.</hi> Men to there aſſiſtannce / they fall dayly out uppon the Enimie / and doe him great hurt.</p>
               <p>Betlem is at Caſcau / where he expecteth Turkey aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>The Earle Colaldo is yet by his Armie not far from Regnits / upon the Budeans goods / and the ſpeach goeth that the ſame Budeany ſhould alſo have ſome Hungeriſh aſſiſtannce to him / En they countred with on another / ſo that many are ſlain on both ſides.</p>
               <p>The <hi>19.</hi> hereof is the Lord Helmſart George caried priſoner from hence to the Duke of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia. In like manner <hi>9.</hi> worthy perſons of the Wenegers taken priſoners out of <hi>16.</hi> which were Examined.</p>
               <p>It continues / that thoſe under the Earle of Iagerſdorp have over com the Dukely Caſtle Neus / and taken <hi>3.</hi> of the Chiefeſt Dukely Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in apprehenſion.</p>
               <p>At Neus are (as the ſpeech goeth) openly folke levied for Betlem / and there is taken on allreddy <hi>1000</hi> Horſemen and <hi>1000</hi> Muſkettiers / and the Governour Loſuiſen hath brought <hi>30000</hi> Duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets from Betlem to Neus / to conſcrive more Souldiors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>From Prage the 25. herof.</head>
               <p>The Execution at Prague over the impriſoned Lords Knights and Cittizens is accompliſhed upon the <hi>21.</hi> of Iune / in manner as followeth: Diz. The <hi>19.</hi> heereof are thoſe of the old and new Cittie caried into the Caſtle / with a ſtrong Convoy or watch / and there the Emper. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners reade apart every ones Sentence / which beeinge done / they were caried againe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to there Coſtodie / and there (through promiſſion of the Commiſſioners) went too and fro unto them Dutch and Bohemiſh Preachers. The twenty heereof are the Priſoners which lay in the Caſtle caried into the Cittie houſe of the Olde Cittie / where they paſſed the whole night with ſinginge and praying / untill the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution began / which was at <hi>5</hi> a Clocke / upon a Schaffold afore the Cittie houſe / and laſted till <hi>9</hi> a Clocke / being al fyniſht by the Hangman / over theſe <hi>25.</hi> ſpecified perſons / as followeth: Viz.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>The Lords of the Cittie-houſe.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> The Earle Iochim Andrew Slyke (Direr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the Olde Cittie) was firſt beheaded / and the right hand chopt of / the which with the head were ſet upon the ſteeple / by the Bridge / and the body buried.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> The olde Lord Mentzell of Budweys / was beheaded / and his head was ſett uppon the ſaid ſteeple.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> The Lord Chriſtopher Harrant (lately Chamber Preſident of Bohemia) was behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Knights.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4.</hi> Caſpar Kapliers / beeing olde <hi>80.</hi> yeares / and the head ſett up.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5.</hi> Iacob Swerſenkſy.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6.</hi> Frederick van Biſan.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>7.</hi> Hendrick Otto van Los.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>8.</hi> William Cornet Clumpſky.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:181298:2"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>9.</hi> Bouſion van Michalowits / theſe were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed / and theire hands chopt of / and ſett up the ſaid ſteeple.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>10.</hi> Dioniſius Tſcheruin / lately Staes / Chiefe Officer / he was beheaded.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Cittizens of the Olde Cittizens.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>11.</hi> Valeſyn Kochen.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>12.</hi> Tobias Steffens.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>13.</hi> Chriſtopher Coler.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>14.</hi> Iohn Schietheys / Pr<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. of Kuttenbergh.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>15.</hi> Maximilian Haſelleck Suſat / Pr<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. of Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / theſe were all beheaded / and their heads ſtuck out upon poules.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>16.</hi> Doctor Geſſenius / lately Profeſſor in the Colledge of Caroline in the olde Cittie / firſt hts tongue was cut out / then beheaded / quartered and hong uppon <hi>4.</hi> ſtakes / in the paſſadge to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Weenen by Raben.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>17.</hi> Leander Roppell / Hedelverghes and other Printes Counſeller and Agent.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>18.</hi> Hans Guttenau / Kaptaine of the Cittizens in the old Cittie.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>19.</hi> Symon Sitzky / one of the Counſell / theſe were hanged out of the Windowes afore the olde Counſell houſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>20.</hi> Nathaniel Botniaulkſy / Bohemiſhe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curor / is hanged uppon the olde Citties Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los / uppon the ſame place.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Counſellors and Cittizens of the new Cittie.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>21.</hi> Wentzel Matſchuropſky.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>22.</hi> Hendrick Bacle.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>23.</hi> George Reſiſky.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>24.</hi> Michell Witman / and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>25.</hi> Symon Hocheketſch / theſe are all beheaded.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Lord William Poppell / is yet kept priſoner untill hes Majeſties Reſolution.</p>
               <p>The ſame day was alſo in a Counſell Servant Niclaes Nailde unto the Gallos by his tongue / where he ſtood ſo an houre long / and thereafter condemned in the priſon / he did the ſecond day.</p>
               <p>More others were whipt / and certaine baniſht the Land.</p>
               <p>Tabor remaines yet ſtrongly againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour / they fall out dayly / and Schirmidge with the beſiegers / likewiſe the Country men in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningreetzer Creyts doe holde them ſelves in Armes againſt the Emperour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>From Prague the 26. hereof.</head>
               <p>The Nobles of Sileſia have paid all there Souldiors and caſſhierd them / but moſt of them are entertained againe of the Marckgrave of Iagerſoory / who hath invaded Neus / and other Biſſhoply townes / as alſo the Earleſhip Glats / and preſently after he marched into Bohemia with <hi>10000.</hi> Men / unto whom <hi>4000</hi> Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have joyned them ſelves in the Shire Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningreyts / and at this preſent are in the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the Smirſiſky / they have ſurpriſed ſome certaine little townes already / as Reyſenberghe / Coſtelits and others / wherefore the Governour van Saſſen hath Commiſſion to meete the ſaid Marckgrave / with his <hi>7.</hi> Companies of Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men / and the Souldiors of Walſteyne / to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with him. Whoſe Folke doe pilladge every where / and flaye al they can lay hands on / wherefore heere is great feare that Manſvelt will joyne him with the ſaid Iagerſdorp.</p>
               <p>The Governour Frenck is let into Tabor / becauſe he hath highly bound himſelfe to ſtand it out to the laſt man. Don Balthaſar brings little to paſſe / but he hath loſt <hi>400.</hi> of his Men before Tabor.</p>
               <p>Heere is great ſadnes by many / conterning the Execution laſt / and <hi>6.</hi> of the Executed Mens Wife are diſceaſed for griefe of the loſſe of theire Huſbands.</p>
               <p>At Brin and Olmits in Morabia ſhall like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>20.</hi> Lords be Executed.</p>
               <p>To worrowe the Schaffolds ſhall be broake downe heere.</p>
               <p>The Walſteyniſh Souldiors would this day have ſaccaged the Iewes / but agreement is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the Generall / and the Iewes ſhall pay <hi>12000.</hi> Florines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>Fom vienna the 24 of Iune.</head>
               <p>From Comorra is written the <hi>19.</hi> of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent / that Buequoy / Maximiliaen van Lichten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyn / and the Lord van Dieppenbach / had given themſelves out of there Camp before Nieuheuſel / and the Hungarians which lay in the woods / ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied out / and ſo invaded and circuled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout / ſo that they very narrowly eſchapped from beeing taken priſoners of the Hungarians / for <hi>18.</hi> Chiefe perſons were taken pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>foners / and thoſe af Nieuheuſel doe ours great hurt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="entry">
               <head>From the Hague the 5 of Iuly.</head>
               <p>In the Hague is arrived a Gentleman from the Kinges Camp before <hi>S<hi rend="sub">t</hi>. Iean d'Angely</hi> in Fraunce / he hath obtained audience the <hi>4.</hi> hereof with the ordinarie French Ambaſſadour in the Hague / by the Highe and Mightie States / and as it is for certaine reported he hath ſought for <hi>4000.</hi> Souldiors and certaine Ships of warre to goe againſt the Proteſtants in Fraunce / which did ſeeme very ſtrange to the States Generall / it is thought that he will not obtaine any thing.</p>
               <p>The third heereof the ſaid States have given the Poliſh Ambaſſadour his full expedition / and it is thought he hath obtained nothing, upon al his propoſitions.</p>
               <p>We heare from Brabant / that Spinola makes him ready to mnſter his ſouldiors / and to march into the Fields / the ſaid Spinola hath received <hi>3.</hi> Millions of Golde and Iewels brought upon Aſſes from Spaine / to pay his Folke with all / wherefore the Spaniards have received twoo Monethes wages / and the other as yet have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. It ſeemes <hi>Don Louys de Valaſco,</hi> is ſett of from his Generallſhip over <hi>Chavillrie,</hi> and the Earle Hendrick vanden Berghe is ſett in his place / whereupon he is gone to Spaine. It is thought that Spinola hath wronght him this deede.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at Amſterdam,</hi> By GEORGE VESELER. The 15. of IULY.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
